Eaman Jahani

University of Maryland, Business School MIT Sloan School of Management

Research Interests

I have two active lines of research: I- Investigating how network processes and social incentives impact various outcomes, including economic inequality, the diffusion of misinformation, and hate speech. 2- Exploring human-AI collaboration and identifying structures that enhance the performance of human-AI teams. To advance these research areas, I employ computational techniques and causal inference in networks, develop new network structure models, and design online experiments.

Areas of Specialisation

Statistics, Network Science, Social Networks, Experiment Design, Causal Inference, Social Sciences

Employment

University of Maryland, Smith School of Business, College Park Assistant Professor in Decision, Operations & Information Technologies

UC Berkeley, Department of Statistics, Berkeley

2022 - 2024

2024 - Present

Email: eaman@umd.edu

URL: http://eamanjahani.com

RTG Postdoctoral Associate

Education

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge

2015 - 2021

Institute for Data, Systems and Society, *PhD in Social and Engineering Systems* Statistics and Data Science Center, *Interdisciplinary PhD in Statistics* Thesis title: *Network Effects on Outcomes and Unequal Distribution of Resources* Advisors: Alex 'Sandy' Pentland, Dean Eckles

University Of Michigan, Ann Arbor

2005 - 2011

Computer Science Department, BSc and MSc in Computer Science

Research Affiliations

World Bank, Washington DC

2022 - Present

Research Consultant

• Working on design and implementation of a field experiment in Nigeria that aims to evaluate and compare the effectiveness of several network-based interventions in reducing hate speech in Nigerian Twitter. A big component of the project is developing an efficient randomization design that accounts for treatment interference on the Twitter network.

Meta, Boston 2020 - 2022

Consulting Researcher, Core Data Science

Analyzed billions of records in the Facebook network and established the link between frequency of
long ties and economic well-being. Furthermore, identified why some individuals have more long ties
and attributed that to certain life events. Developed a pipeline for publicly releasing part of the data.

• Designed a statistical framework for studying the causal link between network structure and outcomes, with fundraising in social networks as the case study. Showed how the random activation of ties in the network on any given day is a valid instrument for identifying the causal effect of different types of ties, in an otherwise endogenous network.

Teaching Experience

University of Maryland, Business School

2024 - Present

• Data Mining and Predictive Analytics (Spring 2024): The course is intended to provide an introduction to the tools and techniques of data mining and machine learning that are central to business analytics, with particular emphasis on classification and prediction. Topics include regression, classification, trees, complexity control, ensemble methods, neural networks, association rules and how these methods aid decision making in applied settings with a focus on R. I gave 3 hours of lecture per week and managed 2 teaching assistants.

UC Berkeley, Department of Statistics

2022 - 2024

- Data, Inference, and Decisions (Spring 2023): The course develops the probabilistic foundations of inference, modeling and decision-making in data science. Topics include frequentist and Bayesian decision-making, probabilistic interpretations of models, Bayesian hierarchical models, GLM, causal inference, differential privacy, fairness in classification, and an introduction to machine learning tools including decision trees, neural networks, ensemble methods and reinforcement learning. I gave six hours of lecture per month, and worked with 7 teaching assistants in designing weekly discussions and assignments.
- Concepts of Statistics (Fall 2022): The course was a comprehensive survey in statistical theory and methodology, meant for junior or graduate student with strong math background. Topics include parameter estimation, hypothesis testing, confidence intervals, parametric and non-parametric statistical tests, analysis of variance, linear regression and computing using R. I gave three hours of lecture per week, updated the existing curriculum, designed weekly assignments, quizzes and managed 3 teaching assistants.
- Introduction to Statistics (Spring 2022, Fall 2023): The course was an introduction to statistics for students without a math background. Course covers population and variables, standard measures of location, spread and association, normal approximation, regression, probability and sampling, interval estimation and significance tests. In a flipped classroom format, I held three hours of QA session per week, and managed 9 teaching assistants.

Professional Experience

Google, New York

2011 - 2014

Software Engineer, AdWords

Worked on several projects around the AdWords ad auction, using statistical methods and building
pipelines for making suggestions to advertises on how to improve their performance in the auction.

Publications

Working Papers or Under review

- Network interventions to reduce hate speech on Twitter
 Eaman Jahani, Blas Kolic, Manuel Tonneau, Hause Lin, Niyati Malhotra, Ibrahim Farouq, Victor Orozco, Samuel Fraiberger
 Manuscript available upon request, 2024
- The Power of Meta-Prediction Accuracy: Leveraging Predictions of Others' Predictions to Enhance Collective and Individual Intelligence
 Yunhao Zhang, Eaman Jahani, Douglas Guilbeault, Juliana Schroeder
 Manuscript available upon request, 2024
- The Network Structure of Unequal Diffusion Eaman Jahani, Dean Eckles, Alex "Sandy" Pentland arxiv, 2022
- Rivalrous Resource Sharing in Networks can Exacerbate Existing Inequalities
 Eaman Jahani, Dean Eckles
 Manuscript available upon request, 2021

Selected Referred Articles

- Long ties, disruptive life events and economic prosperity
 Eaman Jahani, Samuel Fraiberger, Michael Bailey, Dean Eckles
 The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 2023
- Implications of COVID-19 vaccination heterogeneity in mobility networks
 Yuan Yuan, Eaman Jahani, Shengjia Zhao, Yong-Yeol Ahn, Alex "Sandy" Pentland
 Nature Communications Physics, 2023
- A Randomized Online Experiment during the 2020 US-Iran Crisis shows that Exposure to Common Enemies can Increase Political Polarization

Eaman Jahani, Natalie Gallagher, Friedolin Merhout, Nicolo Cavalli, Douglas Guilbeault, Yan Leng, Christopher A. Bail

Nature Scientific Reports, 2022

- Social Debunking of Misinformation on WhatsApp: The Case for Strong and In-group Ties
 Irene Pasquetto, Eaman Jahani, Shubham Atreja, Matthew Baum

 Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction-CSCW, 2022
- Segregated Interactions in Urban and Online Spaces
 Xiaowen Dong*, Alfredo J. Morales*, Eaman Jahani*, Esteban Moro, Bruno Lepri, Burcin Bozkaya,
 Carlos Sarraute, Yaneer Bar-Yam, Alex "Sandy" Pentland
 EPJ Data Science, 2020

- Measuring the Predictability of Life Outcomes with a Scientific Mass Collaboration Matthew J. Salganik in Mass Collaboration with III Authors Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 2020
- Winning Models for Grade Point Average, Grit, and Layoff in the Fragile Families Challenge
 Daniel E Rigobon, Eaman Jahani, Yoshihiko Suhara, Khaled AlGhoneim, Abdulaziz Al-ghunaim,
 Abdullah Almaatouq
 Socius: Sociological Research for a Dynamic World, 2019
- ScamCoins, S*** Posters, and the Search for the Next BitcoinTM: Collective Sensemaking in Cryptocurrency Discussions

Eaman Jahani, Peter M. Krafft, Yoshihiko Suhara, Esteban Moro, Alex "Sandy" Pentland Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction-CSCW, 2018

- Improving official statistics in emerging markets using machine learning and mobile phone data
 Eaman Jahani, Pål Sundsøy, Johannes Bjelland, Linus Bengtsson, Alex "Sandy" Pentland, Yves-Alexandre de Montjoye
 EPJ Data Science, 2017
- Differential Network Effects on Economic Outcomes: A Structural Perspective
 Eaman Jahani, Guillaume Saint-Jacques, Pål Sundsøy, Johannes Bjelland, Esteban Moro, Alex "Sandy"
 Pentland
 International Conference on Social Informatics, 2017
- Deep learning applied to mobile phone data for individual income classification
 Pål Sundsøy, Johannes Bjelland, Bjørn-Atle Reme, Asif M Iqbal, Eaman Jahani
 International Conference on Artificial Intelligence: Technologies and Applications, 2016
- Automatic Optimization for MapReduce Programs
 Eaman Jahani, Michael J. Cafarella, Christopher Ré.
 VLDB, 2011

Honors and Awards

NSF Graduate Research Fellowship 2015-2018 Software Engineering Promotion, Google 2013 Dean's List and James B. Angell Scholar, University of Michigan 2009

Recent Talks

- Network interventions to reduce hate speech on Twitter, Statistics and Econometrics Seminar, Booth School of Business, Chicago, 2024
- Network Processes can Exacerbate Existing Inequalities, Conference Networks Science and Economics, Chicago, 2022
- Network Processes can Exacerbate Existing Inequalities, Conference Networks Science and Economics, Chicago, 2022
- Exposure to Common Enemies can Increase Political Polarization: Evidence from an Experiment with Automated Partisans, Conference on Digital Experimentation (CODE), Boston, 2020

- Network Structure of Unequal Diffusion, International Conference of Computational Social Science, Boston, 2020 Network Structure of Unequal Diffusion, International Conference of Computational Social Science, Boston, 2020
- The Role of Social Ties in Debunking False Claims, International Conference of Computational Social Science, Boston, 2020
- Collective Sensemaking in Online Groups: The case of Cryptocurrency Discussions, Sunbelt Conference, Montreal, 2019
- ScamCoins, S*** Posters, and the Search for the Next BitcoinTM: Collective Sensemaking in Cryptocurrency Discussions, CSCW Conference, New York, 2018
- Differential Network Effects on Economic Outcomes: A Structural Perspective, Network Science Conference, Paris, 2018
- Differential Network Effects on Economic Outcomes: A Structural Perspective, International Conference of Computational Social Science, Cologne, 2017
- Bubbles and Network Structure: a study in cryptocurrencies, International Conference of Computational Social Science, Helsinki, 2015

Service

Organizing

• Summer Institute for Computational Social Science, Partner Site, Boston, 2019

Reviewing

- Annals of Applied Statistics, 2024
- *IC2S2*, 2023, 2024
- Statistical Methods & Applications, 2022
- Social Forces, 2020, 2021
- ICIS, 2018

Mentorship

Mentored several undergraduate students on various research projects, both at MIT and UC Berkeley.
 Example research projects include: development of an online lab experiment platform, analysis of data collected from an randomized survey experiment on sharing and debunking false information

Technical Skills

R, Python, C++, C, Java, UNIX shell scripting, SQL, Presto, Spark, PHP

Last updated: July 20, 2024